Struggling to fall asleep right now? 2
minutes after trying to fall asleep?
Your best bet is simple relaxation
techniques. Engage in gentle breathing
exercises and a mental body scan where
you slowly go over each body part
starting with your toes and moving up
the body trying to relax them one by
one. This can activate your
parasympathetic nervous system and
decrease stress hormones like adrenaline
and cortisol all while slowing down your
heart rate. Now, you want to avoid
checking the time, but after what feels
like 5 to 10 minutes of struggling to
fall asleep, studies show the best way
to rest your brain is to distract it,
but in a very specific way. You need to
do something neurologically easy enough
that it won't keep you awake, but hard
enough that it will stop you from
ruminating. This is known as thought
blocking. And while counting sheep can
help, it's often too simple for people.
Some researchers suggest counting down
from a thousand by increments of seven
or going through the alphabet in order
and trying to name a fruit or vegetable
that starts with each letter of the
alphabet. 20 to 30 minutes in and still
struggling, it may be time to get up and
walk around. Some studies show that
getting out of bed can lower rumination
and stress. And the longer you lay awake
in bed, the more your brain and body
start to associate your bed with being
awake and anxious, which isn't great
long term. When you get up, it's key
that you don't turn any lights on.
Typical home lighting of 100 to 250 lux
is a lot for the eye. Studies show that
even a hallway bulb can raise overnight
heart rate enough to impair sleep. So
consider lowintensity amber lights at
night or none at all if you can do it.
Now that you're out of bed, try and find
a non electronic and nonstimulating
activity under very low amber light.
This could be reading a book, not on
your iPad, listening to relaxing music,
or meditating. Meditation and
mindfulness has been shown to not only
improve sleep quality in the moment by
helping to regulate stress, but it can
also play a long-term role in stress
management and help with chronic
insomnia as well. After the 30 to 60
minute mark of a low stimulation
activity, you can try to go back to bed
if you're genuinely tired and repeat the
first couple steps. But if you're simply
feeling bored or frustrated, it's better
not to force yourself back to bed just
yet. 1 to two hours in and you're still
struggling, you might need to consider
your hunger. Studies show that if you
are too hungry, it can impair your
ability to fall asleep. But it is all
about balance. You want to stick to a
small snack that is easy to digest, such
as a spoonful of yogurt or a handful of
walnuts, which are additionally shown to
boost melatonin levels. The snacks need
to be small because eating large meals
late at night can raise blood flow to
the gut, which then causes core body
temperature to rise, which can counter
the natural nighttime cooling that
promotes good sleep. Also, elevating
glucose levels too high at night can
neurologically uncouple the connection
between your brain and liver and kidney,
which makes you go to the bathroom more
often at night. But what if you fell
asleep fine, got up to go to the
bathroom, and now you can't fall back
asleep? Start again at the beginning of
this process. Passing the 2-hour mark
and your mind is still running. Time for
a worry dump. On a non- electronic
device and not in your bed with low
amber light, write down what is on your
mind. This act externalizes and
processes your concerns, allowing your
worries to not interfere with your
sleep. 3 hours in, maybe you're feeling
physically uncomfortable. Focus on your
temperature regulation. In general, it's
best to sleep in a cool room because the
body naturally drops its core
temperature when it's trying to sleep.
If you can't change the temperature, try
wearing socks. Researchers found that
warming your extremities can actually
dilate the blood vessels and as a
result, it redistributes heat from your
core to your skin. It's the same reason
a bath before bed can also be helpful.
Your warm skin radiates heat away from
you, helping to cool down your core
quickly and trigger sleepiness. Now, if
you've made it to the 4hour mark, then
it's likely time to consider some
daytime problems that may be impacting
your sleep. So, here are the top three
most important factors according to
science that will not only help you fall
asleep faster, but have better quality
sleep. Number three, or the third most
important, back to the topic of food,
how you eat plays a key role and how
you're going to fall asleep, but not for
the reasons you might think. Of course,
some studies do find that things like a
greater daytime intake of fruits and
vegetables is associated with having an
easier time falling asleep, but it is
more complicated than that. It's
important to remember that calorie
intake is intrinsically linked to
circadian rhythm. Circadian rhythm is
the timekeeping machinery of your body.
Human physiology changes throughout the
day. Like, your liver at 10:00 a.m. is
different than your liver at 10:00 p.m.
Your physiological system is primed to
do the right things at the right time.
For example, your body knows when it's
time to digest food and when it's time
to sleep. And these two biological
systems are deeply linked. Hunger
hormones, digestive enzymes, and glucose
regulating insulin have rhythms
throughout the day and night. So, how
you eat controls how you sleep. Late
morning and early afternoons are when
your body is most primed to take in
calories. Eating late at night disrupts
circadian rhythm and leaves key parts of
the digestion process incomplete. Eating
late at night can also disrupt your
microbiome and lead to insomnia. If you
are really concerned about sleep, it is
simple and easy to remember the age-old
adage. Eat like a king in the morning, a
prince in the afternoon, and a peasant
at dinner with two studies showing that
your last meal should always occur at
least 3 hours before bedtime. Number
two, or the second most important,
ensure that you're getting enough blue
or natural light hitting your skin in
the middle of the day. Since humans
evolved outside and under the sky,
midday light provides one of the most
powerful signals to your circadian
rhythm. The midday sun is so rich in
blue light and there are actually light
sensitive cells in your eyes that are
specific to synchronizing the body clock
as opposed to being for vision. These
cells detect the intensity and
wavelength of midday sun. And with input
from your rods and cones, relay the data
to the circadian pacemaker in your
brain, which supports a nightly surge of
melatonin, the hormone signal that tells
your body it's time to sleep. Some
people think that lights from indoor
sources is enough. But it's actually
not. Even on an overcast day, the blue
rich light from the sun can reach like
10,000 lux. Whereas your indoor lighting
actually leans more into green
wavelengths which serve your vision but
not your circadian rhythm. So spending
more time outside in the middle of the
day with natural light is super helpful.
And if you can't do that, being near a
window, working inside but close to the
natural light is the next best thing. Of
course, at night you'll want to limit
the amount of light hitting your eyes.
So it's best to lower bright lamps and
minimize using screens. If you do need
to use screens, it's best to use the
apps that turn them onto a warmer
spectrum as opposed to blue light. And
number one, the most important factor
for sleep is time consistency. You need
to be doing your best to fall asleep and
wake up at the same time every day. Your
body relies on rhythms, and it builds
systems for the rhythms of your body to
best adapt to your life. It's why if you
wake up at 7:00 a.m. for work during the
weekdays, even if you stay up late on
the weekends, a lot of people will still
wake up around 7:00 a.m. on the weekend.
Your body has a system that starts
waking you up around 7 a.m. every day,
but if you don't have a consistent sleep
schedule, your body can't adapt.
Adenosine builds up in your body while
you're awake and then is broken down
while you're asleep. Going to bed at the
same time helps regulate these adenosine
levels. The optimal sleep time will
change based on if you're an early bird
or a night owl. We have other videos
about that, but it's important that you
try and find a consistent time that
works for you. In fact, new research has
found that an unstable day-to-day sleep
schedule alone predicted all cause
mortality better than did total sleep
hours. So, take that in. Your sleep
consistency or inconsistency is a better
predictor of all cause death than the
actual hours and amount of sleep you are
getting night after night. Another study
shows that people with heart failure who
had irregular sleep patterns had twice
the risk of another medical event such
as hospitalization or death compared
with regular sleepers. Of course, the
amount of sleep you're getting matters,
too, but this research really shows the
importance of the rhythm and time
consistency of your sleep. Combining all
these tricks is your best bet to getting
a great night's sleep. Of course, we all
live complicated lives, so the
occasional late dinner or late night out
with friends or, you know, not being
able to be outside on some days. It's
not the end of the world, but it's just
good to know that these practices can
help your sleep. Not only should these
steps help you fall asleep faster, but
they also might help you not die as
early. That's a good thing, too. Thanks
so much for watching. I hope you're able
to get a good night's sleep now and
we'll see you ASAP for some more
science.